Let's move now to allocation methods. So basically,
let's see how we can answer the question:
how do we know where each file is?
First way to go with this is to choose contiguous
allocation.
It is as the name suggests, and it's similar
to what we have discussed when we were talking
about memory. So you put in this case one
file after
each other an if you remove a file like here
then you leave a hole that can be potentially
re-used later on by other files if they fit of
course.
It's easy to implement. Each file needs to
be associated basically with two numbers,
the 1st and the last address or the first
address and the number of blocks.
It's also good for performance if you are
doing a single scan reading and you scan from
the beginning to the end.
And this, of course, is true for rotating
disks, in which
close-by locations are faster to access than
locations that are distant (if it is an SSD disk
it doesn't really matter that much)
But you have fragmentation, OK?
Exactly as you saw with contiguous allocation
when we were discussing memory and of course
you also need to know in advance the size
of the file
which is not really realistic especially
because
many fires can have a
size that changes over time. So even if you
know the size when you want to store the
file, what will you do if then the file changes
sizes and it becomes larger than the number
of blocks you actually have?
Still, as always, there is no
real good or real bad here. It really depends
on the setup. Contiguous allocation is used
when you keep stuff on compact discs and DVD's
and so on. Why? Because there you only write
once, you don't really modify the stuff and
you know the size of all the files you have
to put and those are not going to change,
so as you can see this can be used in practice.
It depends a bit on the case, the support.
What is the scenario you are taking into account.
An alternative way to go if you want to avoid
this problem of fragmentation is to use linked list
allocation. So you use a portion of each block
to point to the next block and use a special
number to refer to the last block.
And then basically you can
scatter around the blocks of a file into
blocks in the disk that do not need to be
contiguous. So you have the first block
O which points to the *second* block address
which is 7 in the physical device which
points to the physical block number 2 and
so on so forth.
Now you need to maintain only one
number per file, which is the address of the
first block.
But, on the other hand, you don't know
exactly where the block number N is, because
now it's not contiguous. You cannot just sum n
to the first one you actually need to
traverse the
all the blocks until you find block N.
As you can imagine, this is not really practical,
especially because if you have to traverse
all the blocks every time to find where a
specific block is and all the blocks are
on disk you have to do a lot of context
switches to access the blocks on disk and
so on. Probably this is not really
the best in the type of setups
also you waste now a small amount of bytes
inside the
the block because now you need to store the
pointer, so you cannot really use the entire
block for your data for putting content of
the file, you need to keep part of it to maintain
the pointer. It's not a big amount of
it's not a big portion of the block, but still
focus on the fact that we always have this
space and time tradeoffs, so in this case
you pay space
because you put it inside each block, you
need to take a portion of that block to keep
the point out of the following one.
You can optimize this, of course, and
you can decide to load
the information about where each block is
and what is the next block in main memory
instead of disk, and this is the file allocation
table
So you can keep a list of all the physical
blocks.
You can keep track of the address at which
each file starts as you were doing with a normal
linked list, and then you can just traverse
this table in memory to find where each block
is. It's still a sequential search, you need to
go 1 by 1 until you find the block you want,
but since you don't have to interact with
the disk and you keep all this information
in memory then of course it becomes
faster. Also, in this case you need to pay
a price, and again it's complexity in space,
because now you need to use part of your main
memory too to keep track of this and you need
to load it when you boot up your operating
system so it takes a bit of a longer time
to put up and so on. And here is just a simple
example of how you can compute the size of
this table based on the disk size and the
block size and how many bytes each address in
the
file allocation table is taking.
OK, here you have the pluses and the minuses
so the pros and cons that we just discussed.
Final one, which is used in Unix is to keep
I-nodes. So basically to associate a small
data structure to each file this data structure
contains the attributes of each file.
You load it in memory only when you are trying
to access the file and this data structure
the I-node also contains an initial
set of addresses. Let's say the
first eight blocks
of the file, so that if you have to pick a
specific block out of the first eight blocks,
you have the addresses in memory and they're
pointing to the specific block on the disk.
Of course, there is no guarantee that you
need eight blocks and at the same time there
is no guarantee that eight blocks are enough.
If you don't need them well you are wasting
some of them, but that's not a big deal, but
if you need more, of course you need a mechanism
to find out also where the other addresses
are.
And you can do this keeping an extra address
to a block on the disk, but this is a special
block that is only used to store the address
of the following blocks.
And you can do this with different levels
of indirection, so this is level one. You
have a pointer to a block that contains addresses.
You can have a pointer to a block that contains
pointers to other blocks that are full of
addresses, and you can go up to three levels
of indirection.
I will show you an example of this in the
exercise session.
Now, if you only load I-nodes for the files
you actually open, they take less memory
you need to maintain a smaller amount of information
in memory about the files that are open, and
it's also proportional actually to the number
of files that you have opened,
but it becomes complicated again when you
have very large files because of these mechanisms
of pointing to a block that contains pointers
and so on. So it works well as long
as the majority of files have /
take a number of
blocks that is more or less covered by the
ones that are already made available directly
in the I-node.